You're watching a video of disembodied
human brains learning to play a video
game. Yes, those are the brain organoids
and they actually get quite good at the
game and were recently researchers have
taken human brain tissue that used to be
in, you know, a person and taught it to
control a robot arm to play a piano. And
you may be asking why? Why would anyone
do these things? Believe it or not,
there are actually are fairly good
reasons for doing this, whether or not
you believe it is justified. You might
also be wondering how? How can they do
this? Each individual cell is alive.
They just make up a part of the whole
and you could clone yourself from an
individual cell if you really wanted to
and make a whole another you. Would it
really be you? That is up for debate.
I really think it's not. I mean, people
have cloned their pets and were
surprised that the personalities were
not all that similar to the original.
There's a lot of stuff going on
including experience as well as
epigenetics. I mean, there's a great
deal of variation and even how you were
incubated can affect that. Researchers
have been able to keep brain tissue, at
least excised from the brain alive for
weeks and we know that brain organoids,
you know, the tiny human brains you can
grow in a literal jar if you want to,
those ones are grown out of stem cells
and they can be kept alive for years. It
is significantly more difficult to keep
human brain alive when it, you know,
used to be in a person just because it
formed around a whole.
So, with brain organoids, you can give
them oxygen and nutrients from the
outside and you can even vascularize
them if you would really want to. As far
as keeping human brain slices alive, you
have just taken it away from all of its
support systems, but there has been
progress in keeping them alive and
functioning.
Now, I don't feel incredibly comfortable
showing you guys actual human brain
tissue on here. So, you can just enjoy
this little diagram.
So, once a patient is no longer using
their brain and would like to donate it,
at that point it is excised and then it
will be taken to be cultured. It's also
been done for people who have had brain
surgery or a portion of their brain
removed and then donated that to science
and it can help us better understand
things like epilepsy and brain tumors.
Brain tissue is treated the same as
other kinds of tissue in experiments. I
mean, really nobody considered that the
kinds of experiments that go on today
would eventually happen. So, the laws
are still catching up and people are
deciding how they feel about it. Now,
what is valuable about using human brain
tissue in these kinds of experiments is
that it gives you a research subject
that is more human. This is really
valuable for medical trials and research
and essentially you can only get so
close to an actual person using other
models.
One of the ones that I find least
ethical, and maybe it's just me, is
humanizing animals. So, taking something
like human stem cells and then growing
it in the brain of a mouse and now you
have a humanized mouse, especially
finding out that they're more
intelligent than regular mice. It
bothers me.
Maybe it shouldn't bother me. I don't
know.
I am unsure if we're ever really going
to be able to keep brains alive in the
long term. I mean, in Beck Sorg or Brain
Ax, I mean, they've kept whole brains
alive by essentially giving them a body.
I mean, it's chemically a body.
Artificial heart, artificial lungs and
kidneys.
But, even then, they've only kept it
alive for a couple of days. Brain
organoids are significantly easier in
part because they're so gosh darn small.
But, they're also fetal in nature. If
you put them in the brain of an adult
animal, they will just make projections
and settle right in. The same is not
true about adult brain tissue. One thing
I can say with a reasonable amount of
confidence is that adult human brains
are just not going to be used in
computation at scale. Yes, that might be
different for the brain organoids, but
adult human brains have already lived a
life. They've already formed around an
entirely different task of staying alive
in a body. For brain organoids, they are
highly plastic and this is the only
world they've ever known.
Yeah, you know, there are data centers
now being set up with brain organoids. I
don't really think they're are to become
incredibly valuable in computation,
but who knows. My money has always been
on physical reservoir computers. If we
really want to recreate a brain, then
there's other ways to do it that don't
involve having to feed your computer.
Now, most of the literature out there is
not focusing on consciousness, whether
or not you could take a disembodied
brain, either a lab-grown one or a
former person, and create something that
has cognition. That's just not the
focus. It's medical research. And yes,
you will find papers out there talking
about the ethical concerns, of which
there are many. And while I'm sure there
are some mad scientists out there who
are fully focused on whether or not you
can create an intelligent machine with a
human brain, I would not say that that
is the majority.
So, still, I know what you came here
for. How exactly do you communicate with
the brain? How do you train one?
So, you're going to take that brain,
either excised or lab-grown, and then
you're going to attach little electrodes
to it. Those electrodes have feedback to
a computer, and then that computer is
going to be able to communicate
information to it. It can take things
like sound or sight, and then translate
that into electrical pulses that are
symbolic of something that that brain
might experience.
Brains, it seems, like order and dislike
disorder. And you can also train them on
dopamine, but that needs to be done
delicately, because if you just flood
the brain with dopamine, it's not going
to learn anything.
From there, brain cells want to learn.
And I know I say want, it's it's a
difficult way to describe this. They
will learn, because that is what they
were evolved to do, to make connections
and reinforce them. So, the big
discovery here is that even in absence
of a whole brain, the brain tissue still
can learn patterns. And here, you can
see the patterns between an untrained
brain organoid and a trained one, who
knows how to play the cart pole game, in
which it learned to balance the pole.
Which, honestly, that seems like a lot
to ask of a disembodied brain.
As for the ethics of all of this, I
don't think that I can reasonably speak
on that. Just because something makes me
uncomfortable does not inherently make
it unethical. I do think we're going to
have to approach the ethics as our brain
organoid models and human brains become
more complex and that that is something
we should think about, but I don't think
we're there yet. I will nonetheless be
keeping an eye on it.
I hope this answered some questions. I
will keep you up to date. In fact, you
have no choice. Live for more.